Guide to the Leonid Rzhevsky Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Leonid Rzhevsky papers
1941-1987
GEN MSS 630
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10.93
(21 boxes)
The Leonid Rzhevsky Papers consist of correspondence, writings, clippings and personal papers that document the work of Russian-born novelist and literary critic Leonid Rzhevsky. The papers span the years 1941-1987, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1950s and 1960s. The papers include material related to a few of Rzhevsky's works of fiction but chiefly document his critical essays, lectures and editorial work. Correspondence and writings document Rzhevsky's role in the twentieth-century Russian emigre literary community in Europe and the United States. Rzhevsky was critical of the Soviet government and advocated for a unified emigre voice to propel Russian literary analysis into the post-Soviet era. Correspondence provides personal insights that are crucial to contextualizing Rzhevsky's creative writing, since his style of fiction approaches that of a memoir when addressing the fate of Soviet refugees (especially in post-War Germany).
Rzhevskiĭ, Leonid, 1905-1986
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Leonid Rzhevsky on general Slavic funds in 1983 and from Agnes Rzhevsky on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund in 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 20-21: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Leonid Denisovich Rzhevsky (1905-1986)
Leonid Denisovich Rzhevsky was born with the family name Surazhevskii on August 21, 1905 in Moscow. He graduated from Moscow Second University in 1930 and completed his graduate training at the Lenin Pedagogical Institute in 1941 with the rank of Kandidat. In 1953 he emigrated from the Soviet Union, teaching for several years at the University of Lund in Sweden before moving permanently to the United States in 1963. He taught on the faculty of the University of Oklahoma, Norman (1963-1964), New York University (1964-1974) and the Norwich University Russian School summer program (1968-1980s).
Rzhevsky published numerous novels, stories, and critical essays beginning in the 1950s. He was active in the anti-communist Russian emigre community and had long-standing associations with the journals Posev (and the affiliated publishing house) and Grani. Rzhevsky also edited radio broadcasts on literary and political topics for Radio Liberty (in Russian: Radio Osvobozhdenie) in the 1950s.
Rzhevsky's major works of fiction include the novels Mezhdu dvukh zvezd (1953), Pokazavshemu nam svet (1960), Dve strochki vremeni (1976), Dina (1979), and Bunt podsolnechnika (1981) and the short story collections Dvoe na kamne (1963) and Cherez proliv (1966). His major works of criticism include Iazyk i totalitarizm (1951 and 1953), Prochten'e tvorcheskogo slova (1970), Tvorets i podvig (1972), Tri temy po Dostoevskomu (1972) and numerous shorter essays. Many of his essays were pseudonymous under the name L. Tann, which was derived from a family name in Rzhevsky's maternal lineage (Von der Tann).
Rzhevsky's wife was Agniia (Agnes) Sergeevna Shishkova. They married in 1943.
Scope and Contents
The Leonid Rzhevsky Papers consist of correspondence, writings, clippings and personal papers that document the work of Russian-born novelist and literary critic Leonid Rzhevsky. The papers span the years 1941-1987, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1950s and 1960s. The papers include material related to a few of Rzhevsky's works of fiction but chiefly document his critical essays, lectures and editorial work.
Correspondence and writings document Rzhevsky's role in the twentieth-century Russian emigre literary community in Europe and the United States. Rzhevsky was critical of the Soviet government and advocated for a unified emigre voice to propel Russian literary analysis into the post-Soviet era. Correspondence provides personal insights that are crucial to contextualizing Rzhevsky's creative writing, since his style of fiction approaches that of a memoir when addressing the fate of Soviet refugees (especially in post-War Germany).
Rzhevsky's editorial work is documented in his correspondence with "second wave" emigre literary figures, many of whom fled to Europe and the United States via Germany in the wake of the Second World War. Much of the correspondence is addressed to Rzhevsky both in a personal capacity and in his capacity as editor of Grani from 1952 to 1955 and of Novyi Zhurnal from 1975 to 1976. Correspondents such as Igor Chinnov, Ivan Elagin and Boris Filippov proposed essays for publication and discussed writings of Rzhevsky and others. In many cases, correspondence that began on formal editorial terms continued after Rzhevsky's tenure as editor.
The papers include dozens of drafts and printed versions of Rzhevsky's essays and lectures. His writings and lectures address diverse topics in Russian literature, including stylistics in the work of Solzhenitsyn, spiritual themes in the work of Dostoevsky, and innovations in the language of contemporary Soviet poets.
The papers also include fragmentary documentation of Rzhevsky's teaching, including correspondence with students and the schedules of symposia he organized at Norwich University in the 1970s and 1980s.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1948-1987. II. Writings and Lectures, 1941-1985. III. Other Papers, 1961-1986.
Authors, Russian -- 20th Century; Editors -- 20th Century; Language and languages -- Style; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Literary style; Russia -- Emigration and immigration; Bakhrakh, Aleksandr; Chinnov, Igorʹ; De Smeth, Maria; Efimov, Igorʹ Markovich; Elagin, Ivan, 1918-1987; Ėtkind, E. G. (Efim Grigorʹevich), 1918-1999; Filippov, Boris, 1905-1991; Gulʹ, Roman, 1896-1986; Pervushin, N. V. (Nikolaĭ Vsevolodovich), 1899-; Rzhevskaia, Agnes; Rzhevskiĭ, Leonid, 1905-1986; Posev (Firm); Radio Liberty
- Correspondence, 1948-1987; Series I; 5.84; (14 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically. Unidentified correspondence is filed at the end of the alphabetical listing.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence documents Rzhevsky's role as editor and writer of literary fiction and criticism within the Russian emigre communities in Europe and the United States. A large part of the correspondence, especially that in the 1950s, relates to Rzhevsky's editorial work for the journal Grani. Later correspondence also relates to conferences and lectures that Rzhevsky organized or attended and includes letters from students. Many letters, while not primarily personal, include details about the daily lives of Russian emigres in Germany, France, Sweden and the United States.
  Most correspondence is incoming but some files also include drafts or copies of outgoing letters. Some correspondence is addressed to Agnes Rzhevsky.
  Correspondence related to the publication and translation of Tvorets i Podvig ( Creator and Heroic Deed ) is also filed in Series II, Writings and Lectures.
  - "A" General, 1953-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A. Neimanis, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adamovich, Georgii, 1960-1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Afanasenko, Liubov', 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aksenov, Vasilii, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Albrecht, Fritz, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aldanov, Mark, 1954-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alekseeva, Lidiia, 1953-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aleksinskaia, Tatiana, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Aleksinskii, G., 1952-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes poetry by Nadezhda Teffi.
  - Aleshkovskii, Iuz, 1982 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Altamentov, Andrei and Larisa, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes a statement (1951) to the International Refugee Organization about Leonid and Agnes Rzhevsky.
  - American Association of Teachers of Slavic and East European Languages (AATSEEL), 1965-1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Andreev, Gennadii
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Khomiakov, Gennadii
  - Andreev, Nikolai, 1953-1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Anstei, Ol'ga, 1958-1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Arsen'ev, Nikolai, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Artemov, Aleksandr, 1962-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Association of Russian-American Scholars, 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "B" General, 1953-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Babenko, Vickie, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Baer, Joachim, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Baker, A., 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bakhrakh, Alexandr and Kristi, 1961-1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ballin, Charlotte, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Balmashev, Mikhail and Maria, 1951-1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bartashev, Aleksandr and Iuliia, 1954-1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Belina-Podgaetskii, Nikolai, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Belinkov, Arkadii and Natalia, 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Benoit, Peter, Karen and Barbara, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Berberova, Nina, 1958-1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Berezov, Rodion, 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Berg, Inga, 1963-1975 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Bergmann, Victoria, 1957-1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Bernal, Marie-Louise, 1961-1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Bernatskii-Ivans, T., 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Bil', Valeriia, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Blake, Patricia, 1968-1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Bobyshev, Dmitrii, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bol'shukhin, Iurii, 1955-1981 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Books Abroad, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    See also: Vlach, Robert
  - Brown, Alayne
    See: Reilly, Alayne
  - Browzin, Boris, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Budanow, Jakob, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Bunin, Ivan and Vera, 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Includes photographs of Ivan Bunin.
  - Butkov, Vladimir, 1975-1981 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "C" general, 1966-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Canadian Slavonic Papers, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Chekhov Publishing House, 1952-1955 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Chinnov, Igor', 1953-1981 (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
  - Clyman, Toby, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - "D" General, 1953-1980 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Dar, Anatolii, 1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - De Smeth, Maria, 1954-1965 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Dimer, Evgenia, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Doctorow, Larisa, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Drage, Valentina, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Dravins, Karl, 1954-1970 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Drerup, Karl and Gertrude, 1969-1981 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Dryzhakova, Elena, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Dubrovin, Yelena, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Dukhonin, Anatolii
    See: Dar, Anatolii
  - Dunham, Vera, 1968-1983 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Duving, Lev, 1953-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Dvoichenko-Markova, E., 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Dwinger-Wien, Waltraut, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - "E" General, 1954-1980 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Editorial Planeta, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Efimov, Igor', 1979-1986 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Elagin, Ivan, 1953-1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 68-69)
    Includes poems by Elagin.
  - Ellberg, Miriam, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Eskul-Jensen, Naomi, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Etkind, Efim, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - "F" General, 1953-1981 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Falk, Knut-Olof, 1953-1977 (Box 3, Folder 74-75)
  - Fanger, Donald, 1966-1974 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Fedorov, Vsevolod, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Fesenko, Tat'iana and Andrei, 1966-1986 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Filippov, Boris Andreevich, 1952-1986, undated (Box 4, Folder 79-80)
  - Filips-Juswig, K., 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Fizer, John, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Foster, Liudmila, 1970-1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Frank, Tat'iana, 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Frank, Viktor Semenovich, 1952-1959 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Frederick Ungar Publishing Company, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Frohlich, David, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Frumkin, Vladimir, 1977-1985 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - "G" General, 1950-1982 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Garretson, Debby, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Gazdanov, Gaito, 1955-1971 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Gazdanova, Faina, 1957-1977 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Gerbstman-Gratsianskaia, Nina, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Gershel'man, E., 1953 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Gershkovich, Aleksandr, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Glad, John, 1969-1976 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Goldin, Fedor, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Grabowska, Waleria, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Grani, 1953-1971 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    See also: Tarasova, Natal'ia
  - Gregory, Paul, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Grinberg, Sofiia, 1975-1980 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Grishin, Dmitri and Nataliia, 1972-1976 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Grynberg, R. N., 1953-1963 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Gul', Roman, 1952-1983 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - "H" General, 1954-1982 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Handamirov, Irina and Nataliia, 1951-1976 (Box 5, Folder 106-107)
  - Hauser, Ol'ga, 1973-1982 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Hellerström, Sven, 1958-1985 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Hermitage (Publisher)
    See: Efimov, Igor'
  - Hlybinny, Uladzimer
    See: Seduro, Vladimir
  - Hollerbach, Serge and L., 1968-1981 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Hramov, Konstantin and Emiliia, 1976-1986 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - "I" General, 1952-1983 (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Iakonovskii, Evgenii, 1954-1955, undated (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Il'in, Iosif, 1975-1979 (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Il'inskaia, N., 1951-1961 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Il'inskii, Oleg and Tatiana, 1954-1977 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Institut für Erforschung der Geschichte und Kultur der UdSSR, 1953-1971 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Ioann, Archbishop of San Francisco and Western United States (Dmitri Shakhovskoi), 1978 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Ivannikova, Lidiia
    See: Alekseeva, Lidiia
  - Ivask, Iurii, 1955-1981 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - "J" General, 1963-1977 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - "K" General, 1950-1983 (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - Kandiev, Iurii
    See: Bol'shukhin, Iurii
  - Karpovich, Michael, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Kasack, Wolfgang, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Kashin, Aleksandr and Iuliia, 1953-1960 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Khomiakov, Gennadii, 1953-1981 (Box 6, Folder 125-126)
  - Klenovskii, Dmitrii, 1953-1975 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - Klimov, Evgenii, 1974-1981 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - Kongress za prava i svobodu v Rossii, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - Kontinent, 1976-1982 (Box 6, Folder 130)
    See also: Aksenov, Vasilii and Ol'khovskii, Iurii
  - Korzhavin, Naum, 1979-1982 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Koriakov, Mikhail, 1958-1977 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Kotel'nikova, Z., 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Krachkovskii, Dmitrii
    See: Klenovskii, Dmitrii
  - Krugovoi, V., 1970-1982 (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - Ktorova, Alla, 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - Kryzhitskii, Sergei, 1978-1981 (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - Kul'bitskii, V.
    See: Swen, V.
  - Kuskova, Ekaterina, 1952-1954 (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - Kutyrina, Iuliia A., 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - Kuzmich, Liudmila, 1965-1981 (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - "L" General, 1957-1982 (Box 7, Folder 140)
  - Leighton, L., 1974 (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - Levinzon, Rina, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Literaturnyi sovremennik, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Litfund (Fund for the relief of Russian scientists and writers in exile), 1970-1981 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Litvinoff, Boris, 1954-1977 (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Lo Gatto, Ettore, 1954-1963 (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Losev, Lev, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - Lunds Universitiet, 1964-1974 (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - "M" General, 1949-1981 (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Magidoff, Nila, 1970-1981 (Box 7, Folder 150)
  - Magidoff, Robert, 1963-1969 (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Maier, N., 1953-1955 (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - Maklakov, V. and M., 1951-1956 (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - Maksimov, Sergei, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Maksimov, Vladimir
    See: Kontinent
  - Maler, Elizaveta, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 155)
  - Mantulin, V., 1953 (Box 7, Folder 156)
  - Marchenko, Nikolai, 1951-1982 (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - Markov, Vladimir, 1951-1980 (Box 7, Folder 158)
  - Matveiev, Sergei, 1976-1981 (Box 8, Folder 159)
  - Melin, Elsa, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 160)
  - Middlebury College, 1966-1978 (Box 8, Folder 161)
  - Mihalchenko, Igor, 1970-1982 (Box 8, Folder 162)
  - Milits, Aleksandr, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 163)
  - Miller, Sonja, 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 164)
  - Modern Encyclopedia of Russian and Soviet Literatures, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 165)
  - Mohan, John, 1982-1985 (Box 8, Folder 166)
  - Mondich, Viktoriia, 1955-1977 (Box 8, Folder 167)
  - Morgulis, Mikhail, 1980-1986 (Box 8, Folder 168)
  - Morshen, Nikolai
    See: Marchenko, Nikolai
  - Mosty, 19590 (Box 8, Folder 169)
    See also: Khomiakov, Gennadii
  - Müller, Irina, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Murav'iev, Petr, 1968-1986 (Box 8, Folder 171)
  - "N" General, 1954-1986 (Box 8, Folder 172)
  - Nalivaiko, D., 1968-1971 (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Narokov, Nikolai V., 1952-1962 (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - Nartsissov, Boris, 1954-1978 (Box 8, Folder 175)
  - Natov, Nadezhda
    See: Popluiko, Nadezhda and Anatolii
  - Neimirok, Natalia, 1955-1964 (Box 8, Folder 176)
  - Neledinskii, Evgenii, 1948-1953 (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - New York University, 1964-1982 (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - New York University Press, 1968-1974 (Box 9, Folder 179)
  - Nord, Anastasiia, 1954-1955 (Box 9, Folder 180)
  - Norwich University, 1968-1981 (Box 9, Folder 181)
  - Novoe Russkoe Slovo, 1974-1986 (Box 9, Folder 182)
  - Novyi Zhurnal ( New Review )
    See: Gul', Roman and Karpovich, Michael
  - Novosilzov, Oleg, Tatiana and Igor, 1977-1981 (Box 9, Folder 183)
  - Novyi zhurnal, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 184)
  - "O" General, 1950-1984 (Box 9, Folder 185)
  - Odoevtseva, Irina, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 186)
  - Ol'khovskii, Iurii, 1975-1978 (Box 9, Folder 187)
  - Opul'skii, Albert and Tamara, 1981-1986 (Box 9, Folder 188)
  - Orth, Samuel and Nancy, 1968-1977 (Box 9, Folder 189)
  - Osipov, L. and N., 1953-1957 (Box 9, Folder 190)
  - "P" General, 1952-1980 (Box 9, Folder 191)
  - PEN, 1967-1982 (Box 9, Folder 192)
  - Pensee russe ( Russkaia Mysl' ), 1957-1982 (Box 9, Folder 193)
  - Pervushin, Nikolai, 1969-1986 (Box 9, Folder 194-195)
    See also: Norwich University
  - Pirozhkova, Vera, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 196)
  - Pizem, Ida, 1974-1981 (Box 10, Folder 197)
  - Pletnev, Rostislav, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 198)
  - Podlaha, Natasha
    See: Tuma-Podlaha, Natasha
  - Pohorilyi, Semen, 1970-1977 (Box 10, Folder 199)
  - Poltoratskaia, Mari'anna, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 200)
  - Poltoratskii, Nikolai, 1954-1985 (Box 10, Folder 201)
  - Popliuko, Nadezhda and Anatolii, 1954-1986 (Box 10, Folder 202)
  - Popova, Tatiana, 1954-1956 (Box 10, Folder 203)
  - Poremskii, Vl. and T., 1954-1966 (Box 10, Folder 204)
  - Posev Publishing House, 1948-1982 (Box 10, Folder 205-206)
    See also: Khomiakov, Gennadii, Neledinskii, Evgenii and Poremskii, Vl. and T.
  - Pregel', Sofiia, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 207)
  - Prizel, Zoia, 1973-1980 (Box 10, Folder 208)
  - Prokopowicz, Ekaterina
    See: Kuskova, Ekaterina
  - Pulman, Theodore, 1953-1955 (Box 10, Folder 209)
  - "R" General, 1953-1986 (Box 10, Folder 210)
  - Radio Liberty, 1953-1969 (Box 10, Folder 211)
    See also: Frank, Viktor
  - Radio Liberty Committee, 1966-1974 (Box 10, Folder 212)
  - Rafal'skii, Sergei, undated (Box 10, Folder 213)
  - Rannit, Aleksis, 1966-1979
  - Redlikh, Roman, 1953-1955 (Box 10, Folder 214)
  - Reilly, Alayne, 1965-1980, undated (Box 10, Folder 215)
  - Remizov, Aleksei, 1952-1956 (Box 10, Folder 216)
  - Rittenberg, Sergei, 1954-1973 (Box 11, Folder 217)
  - Rodzianko, Tat'iana, 1966-1985 (Box 11, Folder 218)
  - Romanov, Evgenii, 1963-1972 (Box 11, Folder 219)
    See also: Posev Publishing House
  - Romanov, Nikita, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 220)
  - Rowe, William, 1970-1981 (Box 11, Folder 221)
  - Rudol'f, V., 1952-1958 (Box 11, Folder 222)
  - Russian Cultural and Welfare Society "Beseda", 1953-1971 (Box 11, Folder 223)
  - Russian Emigre Society of Boston, 1967-1974 (Box 11, Folder 224)
  - Russian Language Journal, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 225)
  - Russian National Union in Sweden, 1953-1954 (Box 11, Folder 226)
  - Russian Review, 1953-1971 (Box 11, Folder 227)
  - Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov zagranitsei, 1969-1977 (Box 11, Folder 228)
  - Rzhevsky, Agnes, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 229)
  - "S" General, 1953-1981 (Box 11, Folder 230)
  - St. George's Association, 1966-1974 (Box 11, Folder 231)
  - St. Seraphim's Foundation, 1973-1976 (Box 11, Folder 232)
  - Samarin, Vladimir, 1953-1982 (Box 11, Folder 233-234)
  - Sauer, Sergei, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 235)
  - Schenuk, Galina and Sergei, 1970-1981 (Box 11, Folder 236-237)
  - Schmidt, Margarete, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 238)
  - Scott, John, 1968-1980 (Box 12, Folder 239)
  - Seduro, Vladimir, 1973-1980 (Box 12, Folder 240)
  - Sedykh, Andrei
    See: Novoe Russkoe Slovo
  - Shakhnovich, Henrik, 1980-1981 (Box 12, Folder 241)
  - Shakhovskaia, Zinaida, 1981-1986 (Box 12, Folder 242)
  - Shatalov, Vladimir, 1974-1976 (Box 12, Folder 243)
  - Shiliaev, Ariadna and Evgenii, 1967-1976 (Box 12, Folder 244)
  - Shiriaev, Boris, 1951-1959 (Box 12, Folder 245)
  - Shiriaeva, Nina, 1959-1967 (Box 12, Folder 246)
  - Shteppa, K. F., 1955 (Box 12, Folder 247)
  - Sinkevich, Valentina, 1969-1986 (Box 12, Folder 248)
  - Sokolov, Vladimir
    See: Samarin, Vladimir
  - Solzhenitsyna, Natal'ia, 1977 July 3 (Box 12, Folder 249)
  - Stammler, Heinrich, 1962, undated (Box 12, Folder 250)
  - Stender-Peterson, Adolf, 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 251)
  - Stepanenko, Nikolai, 1967-1973 (Box 12, Folder 252)
  - Stepun, Fedor, 1953-1962 (Box 12, Folder 253)
  - Struve, Gleb, 1952-1982 (Box 12, Folder 254)
  - Surazhevskii, Georgii, Lidiia and others, 1963-1977 (Box 12, Folder 255)
  - Surguchev, Il'ia, 1953-1955 (Box 12, Folder 256)
  - Swen, V., 1953-1962 (Box 12, Folder 257)
  - "T" General, 1954-1981 (Box 12, Folder 258)
  - Tarasova, Natal'ia, 1953-1978 (Box 13, Folder 259-260)
  - Tatishchev, Nikolai, 1954-1955 (Box 13, Folder 261)
  - Tauber-Starova, Ekaterina, 1953-1955 (Box 13, Folder 262)
  - Teffi, Nadezhda, 1952, undated (Box 13, Folder 263)
  - Terapiano, Iurii, 1960-1961 (Box 13, Folder 264)
  - Terras, Victor, 1981-1985 (Box 13, Folder 265)
  - Thompson-Roos, Eva, 1963-1973 (Box 13, Folder 266)
  - Timreck, Suzanne, 1953-1981 (Box 13, Folder 267)
  - Tolstaia, Aleksandra, 1969-1974 (Box 13, Folder 268)
  - Tostaia, Lidiia, 1965-1976 (Box 13, Folder 269)
  - Tolstaia Mariia, 1972-1975 (Box 13, Folder 270)
  - Tschetwerikow, I., 1960-1962 (Box 13, Folder 271)
  - Tuma-Podlaha, Natasha, 1974-1986 (Box 13, Folder 272)
  - Turkevich, Liudmila, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 273)
  - Tovarishchestva Zarubezhnykh Pisatelei, undated (Box 13, Folder 274)
  - "U" General, 1957-1978 (Box 13, Folder 275)
  - Unbegaun, Helen and Boris, 1965-1981 (Box 13, Folder 276)
  - University of Oklahoma, 1962-1968 (Box 13, Folder 277)
  - Unkovskii, Vladimir, 1953-1954 (Box 13, Folder 278)
  - "V" General, 1951-1986 (Box 13, Folder 279)
  - Veidle, Vladimir, 1955-1979 (Box 13, Folder 280)
  - Victor Kamkin, Inc., 1967-1982 (Box 13, Folder 281)
  - Vlach, Robert, 1961-1969 (Box 13, Folder 282)
  - Vladimirova, Liia, 1982-1986 (Box 13, Folder 283)
  - Voinovich, Vladimir, 1982-1986 (Box 13, Folder 284)
  - Vysheslavtsev, Boris, 1952-1953 (Box 13, Folder 285)
  - "W" General, 1960-1978 (Box 14, Folder 286)
  - Wemander, Lennart, 1963-1964 (Box 14, Folder 287)
  - Windham College, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 288)
  - Winner, Thomas, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 289)
  - Winston Associates, 1974-1975 (Box 14, Folder 290)
  - Wolkonsky, Catherine, 1971-1982 (Box 14, Folder 291)
  - "Y" General, 1970-1981 (Box 14, Folder 292)
  - Yakobson, Helen, 1967-1986 (Box 14, Folder 293)